Okay בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is נג nun
gimmel and we pick up at the bottom of נב עמוד ב.
nun bais amud bais. We read the
משנה mishna which about ביטול bitul of עבודה זרה avoda zara but
we found an interesting discussion of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon with his
father רבי, Rebbe, the editor of the משנה, mishna, about whether there
was one version that ישראל Yisrael could
be used... that a non-Jew could be מבטל mivatel the עבודת כוכבים
avodas kochavim of a ישראל Yisrael
which then he did not include in the later edition of the
משנה. mishna. So the גמרא's Gemara question was, well that seems a
little crazy; like we've never heard that idea that a non-Jew could
be מבטל mivatel the עבודת כוכבים avodas kochavim of a ישראל. Yisrael.
So it said the case was was that they owned it in
שותפות shutfus and this would be based on the assumption that the
ישראל's Yisrael worship of it was really an add-on, an adjunct to
the non-Jew's worship of it. So therefore when the non-Jew's definition of
it of עבודה זרה avoda zara went away, it was really defined
by the non-Jew and therefore the ביטול bitul would work. Okay, so
now the גמרא's Gemara going to do another version of that, so
bottom of נב עמוד ב. nun bais amud bais. איכא דמתני לה
אסיפא: Ika d'masni la a'seifa:
some say this discussion of שותפות shutfus was going not at the
first part of the משנה mishna about whether a non-Jew could be
מבטל mivatel with a reading that a non-Jew could be מבטל mivatel
the עבודת כוכבים avodas kochavim of a Jew, that early reading of
the משנה, mishna, but on the end of the משנה: mishna: ישראל
אינו מבטל עבודת כוכבים של עובד כוכבים. Yisrael eino mivatel avodas kochavim
shel oveid kochavim. A Jew cannot be מבטל mivatel the idol of
a non-Jew as opposed to the non-Jew, the Jew's, Jew's here the
non-Jew's. פשיטא Pshita obviously. I don't know why it's so obvious but
okay I guess obviously because then you'd just go around being מבטל
mivatel everything; there would never be a מצוה mitzvah to destroy עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. אמר רב הלל בריה דרב ולס, amar Rav Hillel
brei d'Rav Vallas, said Rav Hillel son of Rav Vallas, לא נצרכה
אלא שיש בו בשותפות: lo nitzrecha ela sheyesh bo bashutfus:
the case is is that the Jew and the non-Jew owned it
in שותפות. shutfus. Okay, but still what's the חידוש? chiddush? Why would
I think that a Jew could be מבטל mivatel the עבודה זרה
avoda zara of a non-Jew? He can't even be מבטל mivatel his
own עבודה זרה. avoda zara. וקא משמע לן V'kamashmalan because you're right,
there's no חידוש chiddush in the simple meaning of it. The חידוש
chiddush is in the
subtext, okay, וקא משמע לן: v'kamashmalan: ישראל הוא דלא מבטל דעובד כוכבים.
Yisrael hu d'lo mivatel d'oveid kochavim. In a case of שותפות, shutfus,
a Jew cannot be מבטל mivatel the עבודה זרה avoda zara part
of the non-Jew because he can't even be מבטל mivatel his own
part; אבל עובד כוכבים דנפשיה מבטל, aval oveid kochavim d'nafshei mivatel, but
the non-Jew can be מבטל mivatel his half of it. So the
non- the Jew can't be מבטל mivatel it to affect the non-Jew
but the non-Jew can be מבטל mivatel his own half. How does
that help? Now exactly how that helps is not clear to me
exactly because like you know we would presumably say אין ברירה ein
breira and you can't like split it up afterwards. So I'm really
not at all clear about what practical implication that has. I was
wondering that myself. Like maybe if you decided you you know I
don't know you get one of these like like what's the two-faced
God Janus or something? So you worship this side of the face
and I worship that side of the face, so maybe that helps;
but otherwise yeah I mean we'd presumably say אין ברירה ein breira
and I don't know. Okay anyway okay איכא דמתני לה אברייתא: Ika
d'masni la a'braisa: some say this issue of שותפות shutfus was going
on the ברייתא. braisa. רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר עבודת כוכבים של
ישראל אין לה בטילה עולמית. Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya omer avodas kochavim
shel Yisrael ein la bateila olamis. Okay if it's owned by a
Jew it can never be brought down, why עולמית? olamis? What's that
word? Ever. So and you know אמר רב הלל amar Rav Hillel
בריה דרב ולס brei d'Rav Vallas לא נצרכה אלא שיש לו עבודת
כוכבים בשותפות. lo nitzrecha ela sheyesh lo avodas kochavim bashutfus. The case
is is that even in a scenario where a non-Jew is a
part owner of it, the Jewish part will never be בטל bateil
even if the non-Jew does ביטול. bitul. וקא משמע לן דישראל אדעתא
דנפשיה פלח: v'kamashmalan d'Yisrael ada'atei d'nafshei palach: similar to how we interpreted
the משנה, mishna, the early version of the משנה, mishna, you know
of רבי Rebbe and then how he reversed himself, that even if
there's שותפות shutfus and the non-Jew is מבטל mivatel his part, the
Jewish part still remains not בטל. bateil. We don't say that the
Jewish worship of this item in שותפות shutfus is the Jewish is
just an adjunct of the non-Jew. So either way it's the same
conclusion as we came to before except this is a commentary on
a ברייתא braisa rather than a commentary on a early version of
the משנה mishna of רבי, Rebbe, yes.
Just a question, who is רבי הלל בריה דרבי ולס? Rabbi Hillel
brei d'Rabbi Vallas?
I don't know but it's a very interesting name, this ולס Vallas
I don't know.
Do ברייתות braisas have a later chronology in general than משניות? Mishnayos?
What?
Yes, I mean there's a general question about like the relationship of
the תוספתא Tosefta to the משנה: mishna: which came first, which came
second? There are definitely a lot of תוספתות Toseftas that make it
clear that they're commenting on the משנה mishna but there's like you
know sometimes it might seem like at least a layer of the
תוספתא Tosefta came earlier than the משנה. mishna. ברייתות Braisas in general
I don't know. I guess
my guess would be it would be the same story, like you
know there would be a range; but yes but there's a lot
of scholarship on the תוספתא-משנה relationship. Okay so now the next משנה:
mishna כיצד מבטלה? Keitzad mevatla? So now we spoke about a non-Jew
could be מבטל mivatel his and even that of another non-Jew and
we pointed out somewhat the irony, like really even another non-Jew who
doesn't even share his own system of worship or whatever. Anyway but
a Jew's עבודה זרה avoda zara cannot be בטל batta by himself
or by anyone. So now how do you do ביטול? bitul?
קטע ראשו אזנו ראש חוטמו ראש אצבעו. Kata rosho ozno rosh chotmo
rosh etzba. If you actually physically you know cut off a part
of it, you know the ear, the nose, the finger. פחסה, Pichasa,
or if you like like disfigured... הפקר כעפרא דארעא. hefker ke'afra de'ara.
No, that doesn't work. Okay, if you like bang it, you know,
and you flatten it even if you didn't actually physically remove a
part, אף על פי שלא חיסרה af al pi shelo chisra even
if it didn't lead to anything being taken away, ביטלה. bitla. That's
a good ביטול. bitul. Right? Somebody pointed out to me was wondering
about how the Soncino, not the Soncino, the whatever the Steinsaltz גמרא
עבודה זרה Gemara Avoda Zara has a whole picture of an idol
on the front of it. It's funny, but the nose is chopped
off. Yeah, there you go. So it's an illustration of this משנה.
mishna: Okay. Now, רקק בפניה, rakak befaneya, if you spat in its
face. Just spit almost. Yeah. השתין בפניה, hishtin befaneya, if you is
that why they cut off the nose? No, it was an accident.
It was in Napoleon's time. There was a gunfight around there.
Oh, really? Okay. השתין בפניה, hishtin befaneya, urinated in front of it,
גיררה, gerara, you dragged it like in the mud, זרק בצואה, zarak
batzo, you threw excrement at it, הרי זו אינה בטלה. harei zo
eina betela. Although those are obviously acts of disrespect or, you know,
even worse, okay, it's not an act of ביטול. bitul.
Now, because it seems like for whatever reason we'll see in the
גמרא, Gemara, you know, but it does so far right now it's
being defined that an act of ביטול bitul is some type of
physical change being made to it. Why exactly we should draw the
line there, you know, you could just understand that from a legal
perspective we don't, you know, it's too abstract if you just use
words, especially once we even let a different non-Jew do it. You
need to see it defined translated into something very concrete. On the
other hand, worshiping it is pretty... Yeah,
but it's now that's true. That is an act. That's true. But
it doesn't leave a mark on the thing itself. You know, so
to say that the status changed, you want the object to change.
Right? You can understand a logic to that. Of course, the way
it becomes an עבודה זרה avoda zara is not through changing it.
You just bow down to it, you make it an עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. So there would be a logic that just being מבטל
mevatel it with words would remove... It's a denigration. Right.
What if the object of the עבודה זרה avoda zara was a
person? Ah, then...
Yeah,
that's a good point. That's a good point. Then presumably there's no
way to do ביטול. bitul. But I presumably, the גמרא Gemara hasn't
dealt with it, but I don't think you can make a person
אסור בהנאה assur behana'a the same way like you can't make the
landscape אסור בהנאה. assur behana'a. You know, the גמרא's Gemara never addressed
that issue, but I find it like you can't make an animal...
No, that's obvious. You can't make an animal אסור בהנאה, assur behana'a,
so you definitely wouldn't be able to make a human being אסור
בהנאה. assur behana'a.
Can you
make his clothes אסור בהנאה?
assur behana'a?
I guess if you worshipped his clothes, yeah.
We have examples of animals for אסור בהנאה, assur behana'a, the עגלה
ערופה egla arufa is...
What? That's not a live animal. That's... you know.
Okay. Alright, so it says,
where were we? הרי זו אינה בטלה. harei zo eina betela. Now,
מכרה או משכנה, machara o mashkana, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, רבי אומר
ביטל Rebbi omer bitel וחכמים אומרים לא ביטל. vachachamim omrim lo bitel.
So if you now let's say you went out and you sold
it or you gave it as collateral for a loan, okay, so
is that an idea that you're willing to sell it and abandon
it and so on, is that defined as an act of ביטול?
bitul? So רבי Rebbi says...
also spat in front of it.
Right. So why is this right? So that's exactly this. But here
you're giving it to somebody, somebody else has possession of it. So
he might go ahead and destroy it and bang it down for
its... Okay, so that's the question, what should we assume is the
context? So רבי Rebbi says that constitutes ביטול bitul and the חכמים
Chachamim say it does not constitute ביטול. bitul. So for רבי Rebbi
certainly you don't need a physical change. The question is can the
חכמים Chachamim imagine any context where that is... are the חכמים Chachamim
saying we always need a physical change, it doesn't matter what the
context is? Or maybe just these don't get to the level but
there could be cases that even without physical change it actually would
be a ביטול. bitul. So we'll see about that. Okay, but certainly
the חכמים Chachamim in all the cases of the משנה Mishnah. need
some physical change to the object. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. כי לא חיסרה במאי ביטלה? ki lo chisra bemai
bitla? So I don't understand, the גמרא Gemara says if you banged
it in but you didn't actually remove a part of it, what
made it בטל? butel? And the answer is אמר רב זירא שפיחסה
בפניה. amar Rav Zeira shepichsa befaneya. You banged its face in and
therefore it's disfigured. I don't really understand why that's a bigger חידוש
chiddush than the משנה. Mishnah The משנה Mishnah. says you banged it
in. Why, you know, what maybe the point is like if you
banged in a little bit where it's not visible and you have
to be something large and obvious and visible, like I don't exactly
understand why what bothered it. Obviously, okay, you don't have to be
מחסר, mechasir, you have to physically change it. But maybe the question
is what degree of physical change? And therefore the answer is the
face, like something very obvious, something that would completely change it and
disfigure it. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רקק בפניה והשתין בפניה. rakak befaneya vehishtin befaneya.
So getting back to the point that urinating and spitting and throwing
excrement doesn't work. מנא הני מילי? minani mili? Why is it not
ביטול? bitul? אמר רב חזקיה דאמר קרא amar Rav Chizkiya d'amar krah
because the verse says והיה כי ירעב, ve-haya ki yir'av, so this
is talking about an idolater, a Jew who worships idols and it
speaks about you know when he grows hungry והתקצף veyitkatzeif and he
gets angry at himself וקילל במלכו ובאלהיו vekileil bemalko uveiloiv and he
curses his king and his gods, lowercase g, his idolatrous gods, ופנה
למעלה ufana lemala
and then he looks up to God and he realizes oh maybe
I should do תשובה teshuvah like maybe he should be giving up
this idolatry. וכתיב בתריה uchtiv batrei and then it says afterwards ואל
ארץ יביט והנה צרה וחשכה veel eretz yabit vehinei tzara vachasheicha then
he looks to the ground and behold it is anguish and darkness.
So now we're reading this דאף על גב דקילל במלכו ובאלהיו de'af
al gav dekileil bemalko uveiloiv even though he went out and he
cursed out his god and his king and he threw excrement at
it and urinated at it ופנה למעלה ufana lemala and he had
a moment of תשובה teshuvah and he looked up to heaven, nevertheless
ואל ארץ יביט, veel eretz yabit, he goes back to his old
ways. He looks back down to the ground and to his idolatrous
god. So meaning that non-Jews get angry and or I don't mean
Jews but it's not relevant for Jews right now. Anyway, you know,
idolatry, I think that פסוק pasuk probably is talking about I think
he's talking about a Jewish idolater, but the point is is that,
you know, you can get angry and curse out your God and
throw excrement at it, and in the end you still like believe
in that it is a God and you'll go back to worshipping
it. It doesn't mean you stop believing in it as a God.
It's like the whole idea about, you know, about about somebody who
does an עבירה להכעיס. aveira l'hachis. Doing עבירה להכעיס aveira l'hachis is
is different than doing an עבירה aveira to just like because you
don't believe anymore. להכעיס L'hachis means you're still in a relationship. You
know when a kid says to his to his mommy, I hate
you! You're the worst parent in the world, right? But obviously you're
still in a relationship, right? You still so you're not rejecting, you
know, you're not moving out of the house and I mean whatever,
usually you're not, right? So anyway, so that's the point here. Yeah,
you're angry and you do disgusting things, but you're still in the
relationship and you still accept it as a God. Okay. מכרה ומשכנה
רבי אומר. Machre u'mashkna Rabbi oimer. Now what's the debate about? So
so you need something that's drastic, maybe even the point is that's
permanent, okay? And maybe that's now what the question we're getting to
about selling it. Because selling it is not a physical change, but
it could it's permanent. These other things, I could throw excrement at
it and then wipe it off and worship it the next day.
Once I've sold it, I've lost my control over it. Okay, so
that's the position of רבי. Rebbi. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara.
So, ואירי אמר רבי יוחנן ברבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב, v'Iri
amar Rabbi Yochanan berabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba amar Rav, חד אמר תרתי
chad amar tarti of these two, מחלוקת בצורף עובדי כוכבים. machloikes b'tzoref
ovdei kochavim. The point is that you're selling it to a smelter
who is a non-Jew. Now רש"י Rashi says, who said you're selling
it to a smelter? Maybe you're just selling it to a to
a trader, to somebody who does business in, you know, used metal
or whatever. So רש"י Rashi says, yeah, but usually those people were
smelters, okay? So
but the גמרא Gemara really isn't distinguishing. The reason we're mentioning smelters
is because that's like a likely end end, you know, like destination
for this thing is that it'll likely end up there, scrap heap
and whatever. Okay, so so one says...
But what if he like gives it to a reseller or whatever?
Well, that's exactly going to be the question. Okay, so one says
the debate is if you sell it to a smelter who's a
non-Jew. Because there there's a possibility he won't melt it down or
whatever. אבל בצורף ישראל דברי הכל ביטל. Aval b'tzoref Yisrael divrei hakol
bitel. But if you're selling it to a Jewish smelter, then everybody
would agree that what this guy—it's a little bit circular, because if
you sold it to a Jewish smelter and it wasn't ביטל, bitel,
then he wouldn't be able to use it. But anyway, but if
you—but everybody agrees that when the non-Jew thinks, look, he's Jewish, he's
gonna just use it for the for the metal, he's not gonna
resell it. So the act of selling it is clearly a giving
it up up of it, and therefore everybody agrees it's ביטל. bitel.
So by the way, I'll just pause here and say, so according
to this approach, it says that the חכמים chachamim would agree there
are cases without a permanent and a physical change that you act—without
a physical change that you actually can do ביטול. bitul. If the
context is clear enough that you're giving it up. Selling it to
a non-Jew that you expect it to be smelted down and you've
lost control over it and the whole thing, okay, therefore that actually
is drastic enough or permanent enough, even though it's not a physical
change yet. Okay.
But let's say you just put it out on the street, you
know?
Well, we're gonna get to that in the next משנה. Mishnah Right,
you yourself just throw it in the trash. Right. Okay. דברי הכל
ביטל. Divrei hakol bitel. וחד אמר בצורף ישראל מחלוקת. V'chad amar b'tzoref
Yisrael machloikes. No, no, no, the debate is even by a Jewish
one. And according to that, even a Jewish one where most likely
to get melted down, the חכמים chachamim say it's not a ביטול.
bitul. Which would really have the חכמים chachamim still insisting on a
physical change. Okay, so איבעיא להו, ibayalu, now we ask the question.
בצורף ישראל מחלוקת, B'tzoref Yisrael machloikes, according to this second version, that
they they debate the case of selling it to a Jewish smelter.
אבל צורף עובדי כוכבים דברי הכל לא ביטל, Aval tzoref ovdei kochavim
divrei hakol lo bitel, does that mean that רבי Rebbi would agree
that with a non-Jewish, even רבי Rebbi would agree it's not ביטל
bitel because then there's a likelihood he's just gonna resell it? או
דילמא בין בזה בין בזה מחלוקת, O dilma bein b'zeh bein b'zeh
machloikes, or does רבי Rebbi say even in the case of the
non-Jew it's going to be the, you know, a ביטול. bitul. תא
שמע, Tashma, come and hear, דאמר רבי, d'amar Rebbi, נראין דברי nirein
divrai my position seems to be the correct one, כשמכרה לחבלה, k'shemachra
l'chavalah,
when you sold it that to be destroyed. ודברי חברי כשמכרה לעובדה,
V'divrei chaveirai shemachra l'ovdah, and my colleagues there, their position seems correct
if you sold it to eventually be worshipped, that it's going to
be resold. Now first of all, the question is, if he says
that he agrees to them or their position, why is he why
is he disagreeing? So רש"י Rashi actually has an interesting רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi actually says, because what they're really doing when they're saying
their positions is they're telling over the traditions they received. רבי Rebbi
said the tradition I received is that it's a ביטול bitul in
both cases. And the חכמים chachamim say the tradition we received is
that it's not a ביטול bitul in either case. And רבי Rebbi
says, you know what, if we had to decide this based on
our own logic and not just based on our tradition, I would
say my tradition makes sense if it's being sold for, you know,
or it can be anticipated that it's going to be smelted down.
And your tradition makes sense in a context in which it's most
likely going to be resold. So it's very interesting the way רש"י
Rashi frames that. Like we have our traditions, we repeat our traditions,
those are what we're teaching, that's, you know, that becomes now my
position. But then I am able to step back and comment on
like what it would what, you know, what really would make sense
if it were, you know, taking a stepping stepping back from the
exact tradition I've received. Anyway.
But wouldn't the סיפא *seifa* of זו משנה mishna. *zu mishna* apply
only in that case of the מחלוקת *machloket* and not in both
cases of the מחלוקת *machloket*?
That's exactly the גמרא׳ס *Gemara's* question. That was exactly what the גמרא
Gemara
*Gemara*—no but I'm saying but why would you even think there's a
and we're in the—does it mean
אף *af*, אף בצורף הויא מחלוקת *af be'tzoref hevei machloket* or only?
It would have said אף *af*.
It doesn't say אף *af*. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara: *Gemara*
says מאי לחבלו מאי לעובדה *mai lechavlo mai le'ovda*. Now let's unpack
this. What does רבי Rebbe *Rebbi* mean when he says the difference
between selling it to be destroyed or selling it to be reworshipped?
אילימא לחבלו לחבלה ממש *ilima lechavlo lechavala mamash*, if you mean to
destroy literally to destroy, like you're selling it to somebody and it's
very explicit that he's going to smelt it down, ולעובדה לעובדה ממש
*u'le'ovda le'ovda mamash* or in the case of resale means it's explicit
it's going to be resold, okay and that would be interesting right?
Because if it's explicit then it's clear that it's ביטול bitul, *bitul*.
If it's explicit that it's going to be resold it's clear it's
not ביטול bitul? *batul*. And then the cases are all the middle
cases that are not explicit, right? Okay, so that would make sense
but then the question is we then then why
but wait רבי Rebbe. *Rebbi* frames it it sounds like they're disagreeing
even on the extremes. It's not saying we all agree if it's
explicit to be sold it's ביטול bitul, *bitul* to be melted it's
ביטול bitul, *bitul*. We all agree if it's explicit to be resold
it's not ביטול bitul. *batul*. We disagree about the middle, right? That
would make sense but it sounds like no, we disagree on the
whole range. So if that's true if even the extremes are what
he's referring to, so מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר ביטל ומאי טעמא דמאן
דאמר לא ביטל *mai ta'ama de'man d'amar bitel u'mai ta'ama de'man d'amar
lo bitel*? Then it's then I can't understand if it's explicitly being
sold to be melted down how could the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* say
that it's not a ביטול bitul. *bitul*? And if it's explicitly being
sold to be resold how can רבי Rebbe's *Rebbi* say that it
is a ביטול bitul. *bitul*? אלא לאו *ela lav* it must be
that those explicit cases are not what we're talking about. אלא לאו
לחבלו למי שעתיד לחבלו *ela lav lechavlo le'mi she'atid lechavlo*, when it
says to be destroyed it means you're selling it to somebody who
most likely is going to melt it down but not that it's
explicitly for that purpose. ומנו *u'manhu* who would that person be? צורף
tsoraf, ישראל Yisrael, *tzoref Yisrael*, a Jewish smelter. לעובדה למי שעתיד לעובדה
*le'ovda le'mi she'atid le'ovda* and to a worshiper means somebody who will
eventually make sure that it's reworshipped. ומנו *u'manhu* who would that most
likely be? צורף עובד כוכבים oveid kochavim *tzoref oved kochavim*. Okay, so
therefore what you have is is that they're saying that okay my
position seems correct when you sold it to a Jewish smelter and
their position seems correct when you sold it to a non-Jewish one.
It means though at the end of the day they disagree about
both. Like okay one makes more sense in one way and the
other makes the other more sense but they're disagreeing about both. ושמע
מינה *u'shma mina* you can see from this בין בזה בין בזה
מחלוקת *bein be'zeh bein be'zeh machloket*, it seems like they disagree about
both. That seems a reasonable read. לא *lo*, not necessarily. הכי קאמר
*hachi ka'amar*, here's what רבי Rebbe. *Rebbi* could be saying. אמר רבי
Rebbe נראין דברי לחבריי כשמכר לחבלו *amar Rebbi nirin devarai
l'chaverai k'she'machar lechavlo*. When he says my position appears correct what he
really means is when you sold it to be destroyed even my
colleagues would agree with me. It's not like I appear to be
correct and they're wrong. If you sold it for to a Jewish
smelter even my colleagues would agree with me that that would be
a ביטול bitul, *bitul*. ומנו צורף ישראל Yisrael. *u'manhu tzoref Yisrael*. שאף
חבריי לא נחלקו עלי אלא כשמכר לעובדה *she'af chaverai lo nechlaku alai
ela k'she'machar le'ovda* because even my colleagues really we only disagreed when
you sold it to a non-Jewish smelter. אבל aval לחבלו מודו לי
*aval lechavlo modu li* but when it's to destroy they would agree
to me. So according that's really the first version that when it's
sold to a Jewish smelter everybody agrees.
Is it really a smelter or is it just like any random—
Yeah so that's the point. So that's why I say the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* keeps on talking about צורף *tzoref* but רש״י Rashi, *Rashi*
sort of says and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* sort of says we're not
really distinguishing. He means a Jew who's in the business as a
non-Jew who's in the business. Okay but if you're in the business
there's a reasonable likelihood it'll end up in the smelting. Let me
just summarize that. So the point is is that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* basically had three possibilities. They argue only by צורף *tzoref* of
a non-Jew, צורף ישראל *tzoref Yisrael* everybody says is ביטול bitul. *bitul*.
They argue only about a צורף *tzoref* of a ישראל *Yisrael*, by
a non-Jew everybody says it's not ביטול bitul. *bitul*. Or they argue
about both. We quoted a ברייתא braita. *braita* that seems to say
they argue about both. And in the end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
re-reads this ברייתא braita *braita* to say no,
what the ברייתא *braita* is saying is by a צורף *tzoref* of
a ישראל *Yisrael* everybody agrees it's ביטול bitul *bitul* and the whole
debate is a צורף *tzoref* of a non-Jew. So that's expanding the
positions of ביטול bitul. *bitul*. Even the חכמים Chakhamim? *Chachamim* would say
ביטול bitul. *bitul* when you were sold to a צורף ישראל *tzoref
Yisrael*. I should say that what's his name I'm one of these
תלמוד *Talmud* scholars I forget Urbach it was I forget what anyway
tried to argue wanted to say there was like an interesting speculation
this like academic approach is more suspect these days but to try
to sort of speculate based on debates in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
what exactly like the historical circumstances were, you know it's one thing
if you know the historical circumstances and then you read it in
the context of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Anyway there was one I
think it was Urbach I might be wrong that tried to say
that this reflects a reality that there was a high Jewish trade
in scrap metal and in and in used you know recycling of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *avoda zara* and so on. In what? Commodities
business or whatever a recycling of עבודה זרה׳ס *avoda zara's* and that's
why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is pushing to read it or
whatever that everybody agrees by צורף ישראל *tzoref Yisrael* it's ביטול bitul.
*bitul* because that allows the Jews to do their business in the
scrap metal. Whereas the צורף *tzoref* non-Jew that could be the debate.
Anyway later scholars have been skeptical of that read but that is
a position that's put out. Yes.
What if— Quick question. What if, cool question, if the עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah.
the worship itself is בטל, batul, in other words it like the
Greeks— Wait,
that's the next עמוד.
amud. Okay, we'll wait, we'll turn the page.
I know, I know, but we'll wait till we turn the page.
Okay, so, מיתיבי, meisve, I'll ask of this. So we still don't
know exactly, we have different ways of reading the debate, but I
will say a number of these ways, or especially if you explicitly
sell it to be destroyed, the גמרא Gemara says everybody would agree
it's ביטול, bitul. shows you that there are cases for the חכמים
Chakhamim that you don't need to physically change it. It might need
to be permanently, whatever, get out of your hands, or whatever. Anyway,
it seems like in principle there are, everybody agrees that there could
be cases you don't need to physically change it. Okay, מיתיבי meisve
says the גמרא: Gemara
הלוקח גרוטאות מן עובדי כוכבים, halokeach grutaos min ovdei kochavim, and this
is now not about a צורף, this is clearly about a trader.
You buy scrap metal, that's what גרוטאות grutaos is, from a non-Jew.
ומצא בהן עבודת כוכבים, u'matza ben avodas kochavim, and you find an
idol mixed up—you thought you were just buying some, you know, scrap
metal of junk cars or whatever and then all of a sudden
you find this little idol.
Or archaeological digs, most of the time you have like shards and—there
you go.
So, אם עד שלא נתן מעות משך, im ad shelo nasan maos
mashach, if you did a משיכה meshicha before you gave the money,
יחזיר, yachzir, then you can give back the idol and you don't
have to pay for it. Why? Isn't it like you've already now
been קונה koneh the idol and now you're selling it back and
you're getting money for it? So the answer is no,
because—well, yes, you—well, the way רש"י Rashi reads it, yes, you were
קונה koneh when you did משיכה. meshicha. That's always an interesting question,
a Jew from a non-Jew, are you קונה koneh when you do
משיכה meshicha or you קונה koneh when you pay the money? So
one way you could read this is you haven't been קונה koneh
it, you haven't been paid the money. רש"י Rashi reads it no,
actually משיכה meshicha would be קונה koneh from a non-Jew, but nevertheless
it's a מקח טעות. mekach ta'os. I never wanted to buy an
idol, I thought I was buying scrap metal that was free from
idols, so therefore I'm entitled to give it back and to get—not
have to pay for it, because that was never—I never intentionally was
קונה koneh it. So I'm not getting הנאה, hana'ah, I never meant
to buy it, I was never קונה koneh it and I'm just
paying for the rest of the metal. That's okay. Okay,
one minute. משך mashach now— אם משנתן
מעות
משך, im mishenasan maos mashach, if, however, you did משיכה meshicha after
the money, which sounds like—okay, then יוליך לים המלח, yolich l’yam hamelach,
then you can't give it back, you have to throw it into
the Dead Sea. Now why? Even if I gave the money, it's
still a מקח טעות. mekach ta'os. So רש"י Rashi said yes, technically
you could give the idol back and get your money back, but
to people who are looking at it, they see you're handing this
little idol to the non-Jew and him giving you money, so it
looks like you're selling an idol and you're getting הנאה. hana'ah. So
in that case, even though technically you weren't קונה koneh it and
you're entitled to your money back, since it would require him giving
you money rather than just not paying for it, okay, that's a
problem and you have to throw it into the Dead Sea. Now—
Is that literal or just figurative?
About ים המלח? yam hamelach? Yeah, that gets to a question— Does
the idiom mean to throw something—?
Yeah, yeah, that's a whole
debate in the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Psachim whether the Dead Sea
is literally the Dead Sea and so on, there's a big תוספות
Tosafot about it. Before—one minute, let's finish the point. אי אמרת ei
amart now the point is, bottom line though, why do you have
to sell it, why is it fundamentally still an idol that's אסור
בהנאה? assur b'hana'ah? Here, this non-Jew sold it to a Jew. So,
non-Jew sold it to a Jew, why don't we just say that
everybody agrees according to one read of the earlier debate, everybody agrees
that that's ביטול? bitul. So why is there a problem at all?
אי אמרת בשמא דצורף ישראל מחלוקת, ei amart be-shma de-tsoraf Yisrael machlokes,
so if the debate is when you sold it to a Jewish
smelter, so the reason the idol was still a problem is הא
מני רבנן היא ha mani rabanan hi because it's the Rabbis that
say even when sold to a Jewish smelter. אלא אי אמרת בצורף
עובד כוכבים מחלוקת, ela ei amart be-tsoraf oved kochavim machlokes, but if
the debate is when you sold it to a non-Jewish smelter, אבל
בצורף ישראל דברי הכל ביטול aval be-tsoraf Yisrael divrei hakol bitul but
everybody agrees when you sold it to a Jew it is an
act of ביטול, bitul. so הא מני, ha mani, who's this going
like? Why can't you just melt down the idol? So he says
no, שאני התם דאדעתא דגרוטאות זבין אדעתא דעבודת כוכבים לא זבין. shani
hasam de-adaata de-grutaos zavin adaata de-avodas kochavim lo zavin. The problem is
that it was also a טעות ta'os from the non-Jew's perspective. If
he knowingly sold you the idol, you wouldn't have to melt it
down. But since he didn't knowingly sell you the idol, he never
was מבטל mevatel it. He never wanted to sell the idol. Had
he known the idol was there, he wouldn't have sold it. So
everybody was making a mistake, okay? So that's why it wasn't a
ביטול, bitul but that doesn't mean that if he's consciously selling you
the idol it's not a ביטול. bitul Yes, Michael.
I was going to ask it about that פסוק pasuk before about,
you know, about whatever it is and then you know they go
back to it. I mean, we could have argued it is, okay,
you know, if you curse it out, then you— אם מבטל im
mevatel it and then it re-animates it once you bow down to
it again, so it still could have been מבוטל. mevuttal. I guess
what I'm trying to say is you never really were serious about
it.
Well, not that you weren't serious about being angry at it, but
you weren't serious about giving it up as your god. That's my
point. I think the גמרא Gemara is very insightful psychologically. Like I
said, when a kid says, "Yo, you're the worst parent in the
world, I hate you," whatever, okay, you're still in a relationship. תנו
רבנן. tanu rabbanan. לוה עליה או שנפלה עליה מפולת. lava aleha o
she-nafal aleha mapolet. Let's say you went ahead and you borrowed money
against it. So that's sort of like משכון. mashkon. It's not even
as extreme as משכון. mashkon. I didn't go ahead and give it
to you physically as a collateral, I just sort of said if
I can't pay you off, you can collect from my idol. Okay,
or a building collapsed. But it
didn't break? Yeah, it's buried under the rubble. Okay, but I'm not
bothering to uncover it, I'm leaving it under the rubble. Okay, it's
like פסח, Pesach, it's like the חמץ chametz under the rubble. או
שגנבו ליסטים o she-ganvu listim or that ליסטיס listis or that it
was stolen by bandits and I'm not running after and trying to
find it. או, o, you know, let it save itself. או שהניחו
בעלים והלכו למדינת הים. o she-henicho ba'alim ve-halchu l'mdinat hayam.
This is going to be a משנה Mishnah but here we have
it as a ברייתא. Okay, or you just went on a trip
and you didn't take it with you. Okay. So right, well that's
the point. אם עתידים לחזור im atidim lachzor כמלחמת יהושע. ke-milchemet Yehoshua.
So in the case about abandoning it, the first three cases are
self-explanatory. I just didn't bother uncovering it or going to the police
about it or whatever. In these cases, if in the case when
I left it and I went to Hawaii, so if I'm planning
on coming back like the case of the war of יהושע. Yehoshua.
And why mention the war of יהושע? Yehoshua? Okay, okay when the
people went out to war, the Canaanites, they were plan they thought
they were going to win and they were going to come back.
Okay that's all very lovely, but what such seems to be such
a meaningless
comparison. Totally tangential, right? You know, so you could, I don't know,
you could have said if you're going to go back like when
יעקב Yaakov left to go, you know, to what do you call
it, to לבן Lavan to חרן. Charan. Right, exactly. Why mention this?
Okay it's obviously because of that בית עבודה
זרה.
beit
avodah zarah.
Ah yes, obviously the יהושע Yehoshua is in some context of destroying
עבודה זרה. avoda zara, Okay but anyway, so we'll go so we'll
see in the גמרא Gemara, about that. Anyway, אינה בטילה. eina betelah.
If so if you're planning on coming back it's not a ביטול.
bitul, Okay but if you're not planning on coming back and you
just sort of took all your house possessions and you left back
the old ratty couch and the old ratty idol, so and then
you know as you when you're moving to across the US, so
okay so then that's a ביטול. bitul. Now the interesting question here
is is this going like רבי Rebbe? or is this going like
the חכמים? Chakhamim Right? This is nothing physical you did to it,
you just through your action, sometimes even your passive action, you showed
you don't care for it anymore. So it would seem that this
is much more consistent with רבי. Rebbe. Okay even רבי's Rebbe. case
was משכנה, mashkenah, I actually physically gave it to you as a
collateral. Here it's in my house, you're just you've just borrowed money
again I've just borrowed money against it. Okay so תוספות Tosfot, has
a whole discussion, but on the face of it this is much
more consistent with רבי. Rebbe Anyway.
What if it's repurposed? No, let's say he used the idol for
some other purpose.
Like I used it as a backscratcher or something like that. Whatever,
yeah. That's interesting. So I certainly think that according to רבי Rebbe
that would be ביטול, bitul. you know, that would seem obvious. Again
my question is just for the חכמים Chakhamim when it's not clearly
about to be destroyed, how much for them do you know, for
them they seem very much to emphasize its physical change. And even
according to the גמרא Gemara about the case of selling it, it
was when it was like anticipated it would be destroyed. So for
the חכמים Chachamim I would question it, but for that case I've
started using my idol as a backscratcher.
Or suppose you took the wood of the old temples and they
just repurposed them.
Repurposed. Yeah, it's a good question. Okay there's always going to be
the question at which stage would the חכמים Chachamim agree to רבי?
Rebbe, But all this certainly seems most obviously consistent with רבי. Rebbe?
Okay וצריכא. u-tzricha. And first the גמרא Gemara. says you need to
talk about all of these cases. Each one is a bigger חידוש
chidush than the next. דאי תנא לווה עליה de-i tana loveh aleha
if you just said you borrowed money against it, מדלא זבנה לא
בטלה. mi-delo zavnah lo batlah. Okay I would say, oh I'm sorry.
I just I completely misread this. I apologize. I was anticipating the
next משנה. Mishnah. The words אינה בטילה eina betelah are going on
all the earlier cases. Not that all the cases are בטל, batel,
excuse me. All the earlier cases are not בטל. batel. אינה בטילה
eina betelah goes on all the earlier cases. I was anticipating the
next משנה Mishnah where it's going to be cases like this that
is בטל batel when you abandon it and so on. I apologize.
All of these cases it's not בטל. batel. אינה בטילה eina betelah
goes on everything. Yeah, exactly. So let let's repeat that. So if
you loaned it and that's why loaning this would be even רבי.
Rebbe רבי Rebbe. was only talking about משכנה mashkenah when you actually
handed it over as a collateral. But if you loaned money against
it, okay, and it remains in your house, or you just passively
didn't dig it out of the rubble, or you passively didn't go
running after it if it got stolen and you didn't report it
to the police, all of those things are not sufficient acts of
ביטול. bitul. Or if you're leaving on a trip and you're going
to come back, none of those are sufficient acts of ביטול. bitul.
אינה בטילה. eina betelah. And the חידוש chidush would be like even
according to רבי Rebbe. that says selling is a sufficient act of
ביטול bitul. and collateral handing it over as collateral is sufficient, none
of this is a sufficient act of
ביטול. bitul. אינה בטילה. eina betelah. וצריכא u-tzricha and you need to
tell me all these cases.
דאי תנא לווה עליה de-i tana loveh aleha if you just had
the case of borrowing against it, מדלא זבנה לא בטלה. mi-delo zavnah
lo batlah. Fine for רבי, Rebbe when you sell it and it's
out of your possession or you hand it over as collateral, that's
ביטול. bitul. The fact that you held on to it, that's not
ביטול. bitul, אבל and you figure you'll get the money to pay
back, okay, and you don't figure you figure it'll never get taken.
אבל נפלה לה מפולת aval nafla lah mapolet but if a building
collapsed on it, מדלא קא מפני לה mi-delo ka mapni lah since
you're not bothering to un undo the rubble, you're just completely just
don't care that it's underneath the rubble, אימא ביטולי בטלה eima bitulei
batlah maybe that is translated as a ביטול. bitul צריכא tzricha you
need to tell me that it's not. ואי תנא נפלה לה מפולת
ve-i tana nafla lah mapolet if you had the case of the
building
collapsing... משום דסבר המנחא, Mishum desavar hamancha, yeah, I'm not giving it
up as my god, I just don't need it right now. It's
still there, it's not going anywhere. כל אימת דבעינא לה שקילנא לה,
Kol eimat debeina lah shakilna lah, next time I need it, I'll
dig it out. I'm a little too busy now, I'm watching, you
know, I'm watching my TV. Okay, when I get if I ever
need to worship it, I know where it is. Okay, so that
does so so that would be why that's not a ביטול. bitul
We don't look at the and that's presumably what we do say,
because even though you're not bothering, that doesn't mean you're giving it
up, it just means you're not bothering right now. אבל גנבו לסטים,
Aval ganvu listim, but if it's stolen by bandits, I might think
מדי לא קא מהדר בתרה, midei lo ka mahadar batrah, you're not
running after it, and if you're not running after it, you're not
going to get it back. Okay, that case since you really don't
care about getting it back, that I would think ביטולי בטלה, bitulei
batla, that is a ביטול. bitul, צריכא, Tzricha, you need to tell
me that. Now that's a good point, why isn't that a ביטול
bitul, at least according to רבי? Rebbe. ואי תנא גנבו לסטים Ve'ee
tana ganvu listim משום דסבר mishum desavar עובד כוכבים שקיל ליה מפלח
פלח לה. shakil lei maplach palach lah. He says,
look, I won't be able to worship it anymore, but you know,
let the גנב ganef use it in good health, he'll worship it.
So the fact that I'm not running after it means I don't
all that it really means is I don't think like you know,
it's like you go report something to a police, a break in
or whatever, you never really expect to get it back, it's just
so that you can collect the insurance, right? I don't why should
I go to the police? I'm never going to get it back.
But just because I don't think I'm gonna get it back doesn't
mean I no longer treat it as a god. It doesn't mean
I'm saying like, "Oh, this is no longer a god to me."
You know what?
Maybe it disappears,
it's
not relevant.
No, it's relevant because somebody else has it. So I so ביטול
bitul. is I make a do something that makes a statement maybe
through physical change, maybe without physical change depending on רבי Rebbe. and
the חכמים Chachamim that I no longer consider this to be a
god.
But it's no longer my idol, I no longer worship it.
Okay, well, whatever that might work according to רבי. Rebbe I don't
know according to רבי. Rebbe רבי Rebbe, is a is a more
wide open category. But anyway, but according to the חכמים Chachamim, but
but the point here is is that just because you're not running
after it doesn't mean you don't consider it to be a god.
Okay, it doesn't mean you say ach like you know, it can
save itself, I don't believe in it anymore. No, I'm not going
to run after it because I don't believe I'll get it back,
but I still believe it's a god and it has this power.
Like when לבן Lavan ran after, yeah, that's a good example, when
לבן Lavan ran after to get the תרפים, terafim, okay, but there
he was running after. But anyway, even if you're not running after
it, it just means you don't think you'll get it back. It
doesn't mean you don't think it'll be a god. Somebody else will
get it and they'll let them worship it, let them use it
in good health. Okay, one minute. אבל אי עובד כוכבים שקיל מפלח
פלח לה, Aval ee oveid kochavim shakil maplach palach lah, let him
worship it. ישראל שקלן, Yisroel shaklan, now how about if a Jew
stole it? Then by not running after it, you're consigning it to
destruction, because you know the Jew will melt it down. No, you
figure look, Jews are good businessmen, אדי דדמיו יקרין מזבין ליה לעובד
כוכבים ופלח ליה. adei dedamei yikarin mazbin lei l'oveid kochavim upalach lei.
The Jew won't melt it down for its raw material, it's more
it's more valuable for him to resell it. So if it's stolen
even if you're not running it down, it's not meaning like you're
okay with it being destroyed. If you're okay with its being destroyed,
that's ביטול, bitul. that's like selling it to the smelter. But if
you just if you imagine it won't be destroyed and people will
still worship it, just because you're not going to try to retrieve
it yourself doesn't mean that it's a ביטול. bitul. אבל הניחוה בעלים
והלכו למדינת הים. Aval henichuha ba'alim vehalchu limdinat hayam.
So that's a so that's why that case isn't a ביטול. bitul?
But I might have thought that when you leave it and go
to Hawaii, ודלא שקלו בהדייהו, u'dlo shaklu bahadeihu, look, if you really
believe that this was a god and you're going to be in
Hawaii for the year, even if you're coming back, why don't you
want to bring your little god to worship with you in Hawaii?
So if it's portable, you should you should דווקא davka bring it
with you. Okay, ביטולי בטלה, bitulei batla, you certainly are מבטל mevattel
it. So צריכא, tzricha, so the חידוש chiddush is no, even if
you don't want need even though you're not going to worship it
for the year, doesn't mean that you've abandoned worshipping it altogether. If
you're coming back, you'll worship it when you get home. You'll find
other gods to worship in Hawaii. Your question?
The whole צריכא tzricha here is very different from what we saw
in the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah was all about action, even
physical. Right, not only that.
You might have thought that these types of of non-actions still constitute
ביטול. bitul, Which is why it's a חידוש, chiddush, this it's it's
definitely a חידוש chiddush according to רבי. Rebbi I think this ברייתא
works very well according to רבי. Rebbi, רבי says selling it and
even giving it over as collateral is a ביטול. bitul, But loaning
borrowing money against it without giving it over, or just not uncovering
the thing or not running after it, that's not a ביטול. bitul.
Right, within the חכמים chachamim, you it's all of this should be
pretty obvious, but within רבי it's a חידוש. chiddush. Yeah.
So at least according to the חכמים, chachamim maybe even according to
רבי,
these idols that the archaeologist dig up or the stuff that you
can buy from a shady antiquities dealer, these idols are probably not
בטל. batel.
Well well that becomes a question about what happens if all all
the worshippers have died out. So we're we're not up to that
yet.
The ideology's dead. Who's worshipping Zeus today?
Exactly, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. says like this. Okay.
Now let's get to this phrase of
עתידים לחזור כמלחמת יהושע ובטלה. atidim lachazor k'milchemet Yehoshua u'batela. If they're
going to come back like the Canaanites assumed they would come back
in the war of יהושע Yehoshua it's not בטל. batel. So the
גמרא Gemara says
you know, this מלחמת יהושע milchemet Yehoshua affects us by פורים, Purim,
affects us by עבודה זרה. avoda zara, Anyway, תינח, teinach, ולמה לי
למתלי במלחמת יהושע, u'lamah li lemitli b'milchemet Yehoshua, why do you have
to mention מלחמת יהושע? milchemet Yehoshua? That seems completely tangential. So
מילתא... milsa... It’s telling us something in passing. הא דאמר רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda אמר רב Rav *ha d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, like
רב Rav יהודה *Rav Yehuda* said in the name of רב Rav
*Rav*, ישראל שזקף לבנה והשתחוה לה *Yisrael shezakaf leveina vehishtachavah lah*, a
Jew took a brick, erected it on the top of a wall,
and he planned to worship it. Okay, והשתחוה לה *vehishtachavah lah*. ובא
עובד כוכבים והשתחוה לה *uva oveid kochavim vehishtachavah lah*, and a non-Jew
came and worshipped it, אסרה *asrah*, he made it forbidden, even though
you can't make something... a non-Jew who worships something owned by a
Jew can't make it forbidden. You can't make something forbidden that's not
yours. He can make it forbidden if the Jew has done an
act that signaled that he wants this thing to be worshipped. And
then it's sort of seen like the non-Jew is worshipping it on
behalf of the Jew even. And then the question would be, and
we're going to see in a minute, if that's true, not only
does it mean that it works even though it doesn't belong to
the non-Jew, even though it belongs to the Jew, but it might
make it an עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* of ישראל *Yisrael*
that can't be בטל batel *batel* now, if you see the non-Jew
doing it as sort of fulfilling the wishes and desires of the
Jew. So you understand, by the Jew erecting it to be worshipped
and the non-Jew worshipping it, the last two things. Number one, if
a non-Jew סתם stam, *stam* came and worshipped my car, it wouldn't
do anything, it's mine, he's not allowed to give it. But because
I've erected it, it's allowed him to do it and change its
state. And because I've also signaled my desire for that for it
to be worshipped, okay, then he's actually seen as his worship is
seen as my worship and it would be that it's not even
ביטול bittul *bittul* doesn't even work. Okay, so let's take a look.
מנלן דאסרה *menalan d'asrah*? How do you know it's forbidden? אמר רבי
אלעזר *amar Rabbi Elazar*, כתחילה של ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *k'techilah shel
Eretz Yisrael*, like the beginning of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. What does
that mean? דאמר רחמנא ואשריהם תשרפון באש *d'amar Rachmana v'ashereihem tisrefun ba'eish*.
So this is now going to be fascinating. This is like a
great גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. We've had all this discussion of ביטול bittul
*bittul*, so the גמרא *Gemara* is going to say one minute, if
there's really this thing out there called ביטול bittul, *bittul*, why did
you ever have to destroy all the stuff in ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael*? Okay, why don't you just take save one non-Jew that you're
not going to kill him in war, bend his arm behind his
back, and go to every single עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*
site and have him do a ביטול *bittul*? So that's a really
good question. If you really believe in ביטול *bittul*, how did... why
did we have to destroy everything?
Okay, מכדי *michdi*. It would still be in front of their faces
then, you know. What?
The influence... I understand, but working it within the הלכתי *halachic* framework,
right, you know, of... so I understand bib... like... you know, a
student once said to me, look, I can accept that this הלכה
*halacha* is דאורייתא *d'oraita*, I just don't believe that it's biblical. Okay,
so I understand biblically why you destroy it. I understand like דאורייתא
*d'oraita* why you're destroying it, okay, ואשריהם תשרפון באש *v'ashereihem tisrefun ba'eish*.
מכדי *michdi*, let's take a look. ירושה היא להם מאבותיהם yerusha hi
lahem me-avoteihem. *yerushah hi lahem me'avoteihem*. So first of all, the land
from the time of אברהם *Avraham*, it all... the whole land belonged
to the Jews. Okay, which is an interesting idea, right? View it
as not that we're conquering it initially and now taking possession of
something that isn't ours, but we are claiming, right, obviously this factors
into contemporary Israeli politics, we are claiming, you know, something that was
always ours. Okay, ואין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו *v'ein adam oser
davar she'eino shelo*. So first of all, besides the question of why
not have a non-Jew go and be מבטל mevatel *mevatel* it, I've
got an earlier question. How did they... how were they able to
make the אשירות *asheirot* forbidden? Anything attached... whatever, it's all my property.
Okay, it's all Jewish property. You can't make our property forbidden. How
were... so what do I care that you worshipped those trees? Okay,
ואין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו *v'ein adam oser davar she'eino shelo*.
ואם משום הנך דמעיקרא *v'im mishum hanach d'me'ikara*, oh, okay, well forget
that, but there... how about the things that were worshipped by the
Canaanites before אברהם *Avraham*? Okay, so maybe that's why we have to
destroy everything because of the things that had been worshipped even from
before אברהם *Avraham*. So, הנך דמעיקרא *hanach d'me'ikara*, בביטולא בעלמא סגי להו
*bevitula be'alma sagi lehu*. Fine, you still have the question, that's the
question I was saying, go around with one of the Canaanites and
have him be מבטל mevatel *mevatel* everything. Okay, so why do we
have to destroy it all? Just get somebody to be מבטל *mevatel*
it all. אלא מדפלחו ישראל לעגל *ela midepalchu Yisrael la'eigel*, so what's
the answer? The answer is the following. מדפלחו ישראל לעגל *midepalchu Yisrael
la'eigel*, when the Jews worshipped the עגל *eigel*, גלו אדעתייהו דניחא להו
בעבודת כוכבים *galu ada'ataihu denicha lehu ba'avodat kochavim*. They made it clear,
they signaled, hey, we're happy to have people worship עבודה זרה avoda
zara. *avodah zarah*. Okay, וכי עבדי עובדי כוכבים שליחותא דידהו עבדי *vechi
avdi ovdei kochavim shelichuta didhu avdi*. And then when the non-Jews in
the land of Israel after that moment during the day, I guess
that they were worshipping עבודה זרה avoda zara, *avodah zarah*, any worship
that took place in the land of Canaan at that day was
seen as on behalf of the Jews because we also like עבודה
זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*. Okay, and therefore it all became עבודה
זרה avoda zara, *avodah zarah* of Jews. Okay, and that's why it
doesn't have ביטול *bittul*. Now that's a little bizarre or more than
a little bizarre, but anyway, first of all the problem... the question
is, is that just because I've signaled that I like being עובד
עבודה זרה avoda zara. *oveid avodah zarah*, right, does that mean that...
just because I'm worshipping this this golden calf, do I want everybody
to worship everything? Number one, you know, maybe my worship is this
golden calf, I don't care about your Canaanite worship in the land
of Canaan. So why is that seen as an extension of me?
And number two, it's one thing if I like erect this brick
and I want this brick to be worshipped, right, and I own
this brick, that then your worship of my brick makes it עבודה
זרה avoda zara. *avodah zarah* of ישראל *Yisrael*. But it's my brick.
But if I'm worshipping this brick and I want every... I so
love עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*, I want everybody in the
world to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*. But still you're
worshipping your עבודה זרה. avoda zara Why does it make it עבודה
זרה שישראל? avoda zara she-Yisrael? So it's very bizarre the way we
sort of create that idea, but it does answer a question of
why they have to destroy anything, just get a non-Jew to מבטל
it.
People have used things and worshipped as best as they can. There
seems to have been a very strong Canaanite...
That's true. So maybe part of the answer to my second question
about what do I care about what people in the rest... why
does it become עבודה זרה שישראל? avoda zara she-Yisrael? Maybe that's all—that's
why the גמרא dropped this line that it's ירושה היא להם מאבותיהם.
Since the land of Israel is mine, yeah, if you're over in
France or in India worshipping your עבודה זרה, avodah zarah that's not
עבודה זרה שישראל. avoda zara she-Yisrael. That's even though I love עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah that's your own business. But if I'm worshipping the
golden calf and the land of Israel is mine, then I'm signaling
I want עבודה זרה avodah zarah worshipped about on things that I
control, okay? So then all the עבודה זרה avodah zarah that happens
in the land of Israel is like עבודה זרה שישראל. avoda zara
she-Yisrael. חמש? Chamesh? עבודה זרה. avodah zarah Exactly.
Again, the story is still funny, if I put this brick up
and to be worshipped and you the non-Jew came and you said,
"Ugh, I don't believe in bricks," but you went and you worshipped
my lawnmower, okay? Would you make my lawnmower אסור? assur? Like we
never said that, presumably it's only the thing that I signaled that
I wanted to be worshipped. Anyway, but this is what we're saying.
Once we signal that we wanted to worship the golden calf, anybody
who worshipped anything in the land of Israel which is part of—which
was ours, made it עבודה זרה, avodah zarah. made it עבודה זרה
שישראל avoda zara she-Yisrael and now there's no ביטול. And now we've
had the explanation why you can't do ביטול. Okay.
So...
What type was represented by a brick there?
Right. וכי עשו עובדי כוכבים כחוסיה דידך
אבדתה. ve-chi asu ovdei kochavim ke-chusyei dideich avdatah. Okay. So הכי נמי,
hachi nami, so since that must be what happened in the case
of the calf, הכי נמי ישראל שזקף לבנה גליה דעתיה דניחא ליה
בעבודת כוכבים. hachi nami Yisrael she-zakaf leveina galya datei de-ni-cha lei ba-avodat
kochavim.
It's clear he wants this to be worshipped. ואתא עובד כוכבים ופלח
ליה שליחותיה דידיה קא עביד. ve-ata oved kochavim u-felach lei shelichutei didei
ka avid. Okay. Anyway, but that case of the brick makes a
lot more sense than this case. But anyway. So now the גמרא
is going to ask that this case of the calf doesn't totally
work. ודילמא בעגל הוא דניחא להו במידי אחריני לא? ve-dilma be-eigel hu
de-nicha lehu be-midei achrinei lo?
Maybe they just wanted to worship the calf, they didn't approve of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah for other types of things. אמר קרא amar
kra אלה אלוהיך ישראל eileh elohecha Yisrael in the plural. Of course,
אלוהים אחרים elohim acherim is always in the plural. But anyway, מלמד
שאיוו לאלוהות הרבה. melamed she-ivu le-elohut harbeh. They desired to worship all
types of gods. So since they desired, even though their actions were
only directed at the golden calf, if my action was directed at
this brick but I signaled some way that I want all—that I
wanted to worship all types of gods, then anything you worshipped of
mine presumably would be... so I worshipped the golden calf and I
signaled that I like all types of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah anything
of mine that was worshipped, anything in the land of Israel is
also עבודה זרה. avodah zarah איתיבי, eitivi, now the גמרא says one
minute, אימא קודם בהדי עגל נצבו, eima kodem behadi eigel nitzvu, fine.
All things that were worshipped at the time of the calf, that
was sort of seen as an extension of Jewish worship and that
became forbidden. אבל מכאן ואילך נשתרו. aval mikan va-eilech nishtaru. Why don't
we make it permitted afterwards? Why don't we—meaning not permitted, why don't
we say that the things that were worshipped after the calf, after
the Jews did תשובה, teshuva, משה, Moshe, you know, ground it up,
they expressed remorse, the whole thing and they stopped wanting to worship
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah So the things that were worshipped after in
the land of Israel, why are those forbidden? Why don't we just
go say that you can't make it forbidden, it's—it belongs to us,
etc., etc. says the גמרא, מן מוכח, man mochiach, who's going to
prove which is which? Okay, so since there are stuff in the
land of Israel that was worshipped at the time of the calf,
that's why you have to destroy it all. There's something really like
astounding about this like theologically, you know, because you read the תורה
Torah
and, you know, you're going in and all these—all these objects are,
you know, idolatrous objects, belong to the Canaanite nations, we have to
wipe it clean so that it's the land of the, you know,
a land of God worship, etc., etc. Okay, and now what we're
actually finding out is if it was just the idolatrous worship of
the other nations, we would just do ביטול, we would be able
to somehow repurpose it all. The reason it has to all get
so, you know, vigorously destroyed is because it's all really עבודה זרה
of ישראל, it's all like because of our חטא העגל. cheit ha-eigel.
Like to think about it in those terms, that the reason we
are so sort of passionate about wiping out, you know, all the
עבודה זרה in the land of Israel is ultimately because it's our—we're
responsible for it, it's our עבודה זרה and it's all an extension
of חטא העגל. cheit ha-eigel. That's like creates a very different mindframe
around those types of things. Yes, Tully?
Regarding אלה אלוהיך ישראל, eileh elohecha Yisrael, the מדרש Midrash says that
we didn't say that, that it was the ערב רב...
erev rav... Yeah, but we went along with it. All right, anyway...
No, because the calf—the calf was indigenous worship of the Canaanites. And
then when the Israelites went to Egypt, that's what they remembered. Maybe.
I don't think that—normally it's explained the opposite way, that the calf
was very much Egyptian worship, right? Because משה Moshe says,
הן נזבח את תועבת מצרים לעיניהם ולא יסקלונו hen nizbach et toavat
Mitzrayim le-eineihem ve-lo yiskelunu and all those things.
Anyway,
if the example—if it really was the ערב, erev, it would be
the example of non-Jews creating an idol for...
Right, I understand. I understand. Yeah, I'm just saying that it becomes
very interesting now that all this stuff about wiping out all the
idols or whatever really wouldn't have been necessary except that it's all
an extension of חטא העגל. cheit ha-eigel. Anyway, so that's the point
why it says that if you leave it to come back, it's
like, it's like the time of, what do you call it, of
יהושע, Yehoshua, because the point is, I mean, so how does it
tie into this point about the מלחמה milchamah of יהושע? Yehoshua? So
let me just see how רש"י Rashi explains that.
Oh yeah, that's because of the word of, okay, because there's a
question here, the top line of the גמרא you'll see a little
א, aleph, right? It says אם עתידין להחזיר כמלחמת יהושע אינה בטלה,
im atidin lehachazir kemilchemet Yehoshua einah betelah, so some just add עולמית.
olamit. It's never בטלה, betelah, עולמית. olamit. So what's the force of
the word עולמית? olamit? So once we sort of are now saying
that by referencing מלחמת יהושע, milchemet Yehoshua, what we're meaning to reference
is is that in when they conquered at the time of יהושע,
Yehoshua, the reason that they couldn't do ביטול was because, you know,
we're sort of referencing this idea of עולמית, olamit, that what happened
in the time of יהושע Yehoshua wasn't open for ביטול because of
the way in which it ultimately was, you know, עבודה זרה of
ישראל. So that's why when we're discussing leaving and coming back and
whatever, even though of course there you don't need to reference יהושע,
Yehoshua, it just means that there's no ביטול, we're referencing this idea
that the עבודה זרה in ארץ ישראל was not בטל עולמית olamit
because it was ultimately connected to the חטא העגל. cheit ha-eigel. Okay,
let's look at the next משנה. mishnah. עבודת כוכבים שהניחו עובדיה בשעת
שלום. avodat kochavim shehenichu ovdeiha bishat shalom.
So now it's okay, and there's a similar to the idea of
leaving it, okay. So if it was left and they're not planning
on coming back and it was a peaceful time, they were just
moving and they didn't take their עבודה זרה with them, so מותרת,
mutteret, it's permissible. בשעת מלחמה, bishat milchamah,
if it's at a time of war and then the leaving of
it doesn't prove anything, they were running out so that they would
not get killed by the incoming troops, אסורה, assurah, it remains forbidden.
Okay, במשאות של מלכים הרי אלו מותרות. bimsa'ot shel melachim harei elu
muttarot. Now if they build these sort of like platforms for when
apparently the way רש"י Rashi explains it, when kings are passing through,
you erect these pedestals and you put idols on them in the
path that you think that the king will take, הרי אלו מותרות,
harei elu muttarot, they're permissible מפני שמעמידים אותה בשעה שמלכים עוברים, mipnei
she-maamidim otah besha'ah shemelachim overim, they're only put up temporarily. Why that
should mean they're permissible is not clear, we'll see in a minute.
Okay, but anyway here you have the idea that it's been abandoned
by the non-Jews, but that's an act of abandonment, right? The question
is of course what happens when all the worshippers have died out?
Nobody particularly did an act of abandonment, nobody did an act of
ביטול, but nobody is sustaining it as a god either. Okay, but
anyway but this is this act of abandonment. What's also not clear
about this משנה mishnah is is this משנה mishnah going according to
רבי or is it going even according to the חכמים, right? The
חכמים who emphasized you needed some physical or permanent change or
whatever, here it's not permanently changed, maybe the incoming troops are going
to take it and they'll possess it and they'll worship it. So
this obviously works better according to רבי, but it's being taught סתם,
it sounds like it's according to all opinions. Let's take a look
at the
גמרא. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav, בית
נמרוד הרי היא כעבודת כוכבים שהניחו עובדיה. Beis Nimrod harei hi ke-avodat
kochavim shehenichu ovdeiha. So it's interesting they call it the House of
Nimrod, but רש"י Rashi says it means actually the מגדל בבל. Migdal
Bavel.
Okay, if you go and you ever actually are able ever able
to find the מגדל בבל, Migdal Bavel, then it is
then הרי היא כעבודת כוכבים שהניחו עובדיה בשעת שלום. harei hi ke-avodat
kochavim shehenichu ovdeiha bishat shalom. Don't think that it's permissible, now I
presume that they worshipped the מגדל בבל, Migdal Bavel, which is interesting.
Don't think it's permissible because they say oh they left it בשעת
מלחמה, bishat milchamah, God scattered them, they didn't have a choice but
to leave. Okay, no, it's actually considered leaving it בשעת שלום bishat
shalom and it remains forbidden. Why? ומו... umu... I'm sorry, I got
that reversed. I don't know where my head is today. Don't think
it's like leaving it בשעת מלחמה bishat milchamah and it remains אסור,
assur, it's leaving it בשעת שלום bishat shalom and it's מותר. muttar.
Now why is it leaving it בשעת שלום? bishat shalom? They had
no choice but to leave. אף על גב דכי בדרנהו רחמנא, af
al gav deki baddarnehu Rachmana, even though when God scattered them, כשעת
מלחמה דמי, keshat milchamah dami, it's like בשעת מלחמה bishat milchamah and
therefore it should remain forbidden, אי בעו למהדר הדור, ei ba'u lemehedar
hadur,
but they always could have come back after they were scattered. Okay,
nobody was preventing them from coming back. מדילא הדור בטולי בטלה, midela
hadur bittulei bittelah, and since they didn't come back, that's an act
of ביטול. Okay, so this is very interesting, right? It means the
passive choice not to return is considered an act of ביטול. Now
again think about the earlier גמרא. My עבודה זרה got stolen, it
fell under rubble, my passive choice of not to uncover it is
not an act of ביטול. So here my passive choice not to
return is an act of ביטול? Why when I'm not running after
it and somebody else has it, that's not ביטול, but when it's
there and I could always go back to it anytime I want,
like I don't know, I really don't get it fully. Okay, but
anyway but that's saying that this does constitute an act of ביטול,
which is important, which gives more broader permission, that even though if
non-Jews abandon a place or whatever and you say oh well they
were chased out, ah, but as long as they had an opportunity
to come back, you know, it is an act of ביטול. Actually...
רמב״ם, Rambam, I don't know why my head has just gone here,
but it did, רמב״ם Rambam in his famous like אגרת השמד, Iggeret
HaShmad, which talks about, you know, Jews that, you know, that converted
because of a threat of being, of being, you know, martyred and
put to death and so on, so it's an אונס, onus, you
know, and רמב״ם Rambam was very sympathetic, you are אנוסים, anusim, and
you should come back, but at the same time רמב״ם Rambam says,
however, says if after that moment of threat has passed and now
you actually have an opportunity to come back and you without consequence
and you're still not coming back and you're still staying as these,
you know, crypto-Christians, you know, Jews or whatever and so on, he
says, he says you can't call that אונס onus anymore. Then you're
actually, now he's not so harsh because, you know, the circumstances still
it's not so trivial based on the circumstances you're in to change
gear, but at the same time, you know, you you have to
acknowledge that now you actually have an opportunity to do something about
it. So it's very interesting, it's sort of like the point being
made here. Okay, so the גמרא says like this: בימסאות של מלכים
הרי אלו
מותרות.
Bimasot she’mlachim
harei elu mutarot. וכי מפני שמעמידין אותה בשעת שמלכים עוברים מותרות? Ve’chi
mipnei she’ma’amidun otah bish’at she’mlachim ovrim mutarot? What, just because you erect
it when the kings pass by it's מותר? muttar? I mean, you
still you made it a תשמיש tashmish of עבודה זרה and who
who says you were ever מבטל it? אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן הכי קאמר מפני שמעמידין אותה בשעת שמלכים עוברים ומלכים
מניחין דרך זו והולכים בדרך אחרת. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan hachi ka’amar: mipnei she’ma’amidun otah bish’at she’mlachim ovrim u’mlachim manichin
derech zo ve’holchim b’derech acheret. Okay, it's because you know even when
you erect it that the kings are not, you know, that the
kings might choose to take another path through the town and then,
you know, it's never going to have been actually like it'll never
have been meant to have been used at all sort of. And
it's not exactly clear why this works. If you look at רש״י,
Rashi רש״י Rashi says,
רש״י says where are we, by by six lines from the bottom:
ואין חוששין להם הלכך לאו משמשי עבודת כוכבים חשיבי. ve’ein choshshim lahem,
hilkach lav mishamshei avodat kochavim chashivei. So since the kings don't care
for the idols because they're going on a different path, what is
that a ביטול of the idol? Or did that mean that since
it was always done מצד ספק, misad safek, you never knew that
the king was going to be there, so it was never לכתחילה
lechat’chilah תשמיש, tashmish,
yeah it's the stages of the the stage.
Right, but it's like it's still not exactly clear. If you look
at תוספות, Tosfot תוספות Tosfot says: והולכים בדרך אחרת והעובדי כוכבים שעבדום
לא עשאום עבודת כוכבים אלא לצורך מלכים. ve’holchim b’derech acheret, ve’hakumim she’avduam
lo asa’um avodat kochavim ela l’tzorech melachim.
So תוספות Tosfot says it's not that it was never a תשמיש
tashmish because the, you know, it still was a platform for the
idol. No, the idol was never an idol. שכיון שאין המלכים חוששים
בהם גם הם מבטלין אותה. She’kevan she’ein hamlachim choshshim bahem, gam heim
mevatlim otah. Okay, so תוספות tries to make it fit more into
patterns we know like we're only erecting this because we as an
honor to the king, we don't really believe in this otherwise we
would have had it here in general. If the king didn't walk
by this path, we we don't care about it. Anyway, still a
little bit unclear. All right, I'm going back to the
גמרא. כי אתא עולא יתיב אבימצתא פגימתא. Ki ata Ulla yasiv abimtza
pagima. He sat on a on a chipped like a platform. Okay,
it must have been a low platform that had been used for
עבודה זרה. אמר ליה רב יהודה לעולא, Amar lei Rav Yehuda le’Ulla,
so רב יהודה said to עולא: Ulla: והא רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו,
ve’ha Rav ve’Shmuel d’amri tuvai, but רב and שמואל Shmuel don't they
both say בימוס שנפגם אסור? bimus she’nifgam assur? Even if it's been
chipped it's forbidden? ואפילו למאן דאמר אין עובדים לשברים, Ve’afillu l’man d’amar
ein ovdim l’shvarim, even if you say that
people don't worship
the broken pieces if you remember that was a debate before that
even an עבודה זרה that breaks by itself maybe is permissible. הני
מילי עבודת כוכבים, Hani mili avodat kochavim, that's an עבודה זרה that
breaks by itself, it becomes
permissible, דזילא בה מילתא למפלח לשברים d’zila bah milta l’miflach l’shvarim because
it's considered disgraceful to worship broken pieces. So that's why we could
say it's automatic ביטול if the עבודה זרה breaks into pieces.
Okay, אבל האי, aval hai, but a platform, a תשמיש עבודה זרה,
tashmish avodah zarah, לא אכפת ליה, lo ichpat lei, they'll use a
platform even if it's chipped. Okay, this is now a new interesting
discussion. We had a discussion before if an עבודה זרה automatically breaks
by itself, didn't undergo an act of ביטול, just broke by itself,
does it remain אסור? assur? And here the question is what if
a תשמיש עבודה זרה? tashmish avodah zarah? Now if it totally broke
presumably it would be מותר, muttar, it's no longer can function as
a תשמיש. tashmish. But if it's a little chipped, he says they'll
still use it. Why should that be make it permissible?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said: just because it's chipped doesn't
mean that it's stopped functioning as a platform as a תשמיש. tashmish.
אמר ליה מאן יהיב לן מעפרא דרב ושמואל ומלינן עינַן? Amar lei
man yahiv lan me’afra d’Rav ve’Shmuel u’mal’inan einan?
Who would give us, you know, from the dust of
רב and שמואל Shmuel like you would expect it to say something
positive, like we would kiss the dust of their feet. But he
says, ah, if only we had the dust of their feet we
could fill our eyes with it, which means that it would blind
us, which actually means like that's not helpful, like I don't, you
know, I think that that's a non-illuminating approach, you know, that would
be approach that would fill my eyes with dirt. Okay, הא רבי
יוחנן וריש לקיש דאמרי תרווייהו: ha Rabbi Yochanan ve’Resh Lakish d’amri tuvai:
you have רב and שמואל, Shmuel, I got רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. And what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish say is: בימוס שנפגם מותר, bimus she’nifgam muttar,
that a platform that's chipped is permissible. And in the opposite direction:
ואפילו למאן דעבדי לשברים, ve’afillu l’man d’ovdim l’shvarim, even if you say
that people still worship the broken pieces. pieces of an idol that
broke, that an idol that broke by itself is not ביטול *bittul*.
הני מילי עובדי כוכבים *hani milei ovdei chochavim*, that's an idol that
they really hold onto its status. דכיון דפלחא *d'keivan d'palcha*, once they
once worshipped it, זילא בה מלתא לביטולי *zila ba milsa levatulei*, they
they don't want to stop worshipping it, so even if it's broken,
they're not nullifying it and it retains its status even if the
idol broke. אבל הני *aval hani*, but a just a stone that
was used as a platform, שקלי להאי ומייתי בימוס אחרינא *shaklei lehai
umaisei bimus achrina*, if it's got a chip, alright, we'll use a
different stone. Now of course you wonder like what are you talking
about? Are you talking about like a random boulder? Are you talking
about something that they carved really nice and they, you know, made
etchings in it? So a little chip you don't throw out a
whole big nice stone, you know, it's not it takes effort to
make a platform. But anyway, but he says a difference. He says
no, I actually believe that if this תשמיש *tashmish* is a little
chipped, they are מבטל *mevatel* it, they'll get a nice a better
one, they're more ready to exchange it. So here becomes the question
of a תשמיש *tashmish* that was נשתבר *nishtaber* and not even נשתבר
*nishtaber*, just even a little chipped. Does that become an automatic ביטול
*bittul*, or a chip off the old block, does it become it's
definitely not a ביטול *bittul* was the approach of Rav and Shmuel
as opposed to the approach of Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish who
say, oh, even a tiny chip definitely is a ביטול *bittul* by
a תשמיש *tashmish*. Okay, תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן *tanya kevata de-Rabbi Yochanan*,
we'll read one more line. We taught like Rabbi Yochanan וריש לקיש
*ve-Reish Lakish*, בימוס שנפגם מותר *bimus shenifgam mutar*, if a platform gets
chipped, that makes it permissible. מזבח שנפגם *mizbeach shenifgam*, if an altar
an idolatrous altar is chipped, אסור *assur*, it remains forbidden עד שיינתץ
רובו *ad she-yinateitz rubo*, until the majority gets deconstructed because that's maybe
even though that is also a תשמיש *tashmish*, it takes a lot
more effort to build an altar, so therefore they do not discard
it as soon as it gets chipped. A platform maybe they discard,
but an altar not, and therefore an altar is not considered a
ביטול *bittul* as a תשמיש *tashmish* until it's completely, you know, un-
destroyed. היכי דמי בימוס היכי דמי מזבח *heichi dami bimus heichi dami
mizbeach*? What's the difference? אמר רבי יעקב בר אידי אמר רבי יוחנן
*amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi amar Rabbi Yochanan*, בימוס אבן אחת *bimus
even achas*, בימוס *bimus* is a single stone, מזבח אבנים הרבה *mizbeach
avanim harbei*, and a מזבח *mizbeach* is multiple stones constructed, and we
will pick up with this on Shabbos.